We tested it again on iOS and on Android
on different cohorts of users, new
users, existing users, reactivated
users. We kept getting similar results.
We felt pretty confident that raising
the price, we were not going to lose any
money. If this is really going to unlock
paid acquisition and some other things
such as the marginal cost of AI features
for us, then why not do it? It gives our
marketing team so much more room to
operate. Hello, I'm your host David
Barnard. Today's conversation is shorter
than usual and will be featured in
Revenue Cat's State of Subscription Apps
Report.
Each episode in this series will explore
one crucial topic and share actionable
insights from top subscription app
operators. With me today, Patrick Rills,
Chief Product and Technology Officer at
Lose It. On the podcast, I talked with
Patrick about testing prices from $5 all
the way to $120 per year. Why rising
customer acquisition costs forced a
pricing rethink and how raising the
price allows them to discount more
aggressively. Hey Patrick, thanks so
much for joining me on the podcast
today. Hey David, I'm glad to be on. I
think I've almost listened to every
single episode of Sub Club. I think
maybe there might be just a handful that
I've I've never listened to. So, this is
a dream come true for me. That's
amazing. I didn't even know that. Thanks
for Thanks for saying that. Well, I
wanted to have you on cuz you know, I've
I've talked about Lose It before, a
storied app. I don't know if you know
this. I I was actually building a like
health and wellness app in 2008 when
Lose It launched. So, I've been
following Lose It for what is that? 17
years now?
>> We are in our 18th year, yeah. Yeah,
exactly. So, this year y'all doubled the
price, which is a is a big deal. And I
mean, you know, everybody's doing price
testing and you've done a ton of price
testing, but for a storied app like Lose
It with so much momentum, being part of
a publicly traded company, doubling your
prices a big deal. This isn't the
average like indie app that was charging
10 bucks a year doubling to 20. This was
a big deal. So, I wanted to start with
kind of the the thoughts behind it and
some lessons that folks can take away
from why you did it and what you're
learning along the way.
Yeah, sure. We've had the same price
since we launched the premium product in
2012, which is actually before I started
at Lose It. The original price for the
premium product, the base price, was
always $39.99 per year,
even before we implemented auto-renewing
subscriptions. The original product in
the app was just a consumable in-app
purchase, and then we would have to like
send out emails to beg people to renew.
Then when auto-renewing subscriptions
came out, that fundamentally changed our
business.
But, over those years since we've held
the price constant, a lot has changed in
the app economy.
Particularly,
I'd say the biggest push for this has
been the cost of acquisition has gone
up, especially since
CACs are going up on all channels
because of increased competition, and
there's been some restrictions. Meta
recently restricted health and wellness
apps how they can advertise on their
platform.
It's driven up costs, and so that's been
the main driver, besides just other
things being more expensive than they
were in 2012. And that's kind of been a
historical thing for Lose It as well,
right? Is it you had depended way more
on organic search. I mean, having been
in the App Store 18 years,
you were really highly ranked for, you
know, diet app and weight loss and like
all these like really big keywords. So,
historically, the app did rely more on
this organic push, but then in the last
few years, you have been pushing more
into user acquisition, right? That's
right. Yeah, we had built up a moat
since we had been in the App Store since
November of 2008 and we had built up
quite a moat with hundreds of thousands
of five-star reviews showing up in the
the top of the searches and that still
happens, but as competition grows,
that's going to happen less and less.
So, we are looking to really ramp up our
[snorts] paid acquisition and we need
the economics for that to be a little
bit better. Uh at a $40 price point,
it's, you know, much harder than at an
$80 price point to get the ROAS that you
need. Yeah, absolutely. So, I know
you've done some price testing in the in
the past. Explain some of the price
testing that led up to this, kind of the
the lessons you learned as you tried
these other prices. We didn't come about
keeping the price at $40 lightly. Over
those years, we have been testing
constantly up and down the demand curve.
We've tested everything from over the
years from $5 a year to $120 a year.
And usually what you find is that when
you raise the price, conversions go down
and when you lower the price,
conversions go up, of course, but
usually it doesn't net out. Like we felt
like at $40 with the sale system that we
had, we were at a pretty good
equilibrium. Like we couldn't figure out
a pricing structure that could beat it
consistently.
However, in late 2024, we started price
testing again as, you know, phones are
getting more expensive, our competitors
are getting
a lot more expensive and so we decided
to test it again, like maybe they're on
to something. And when we tested it for
the for the first time, it broke even.
So, I'd say like the the net the net
broke even.
That was quite a surprise for us because
that had never happened before.
And so, we tested it again on iOS
and on Android
on different cohorts of users, new
users, existing users, reactivated
users.
We kept getting similar results. We felt
pretty confident that raising the price
we were not going to lose any money. If
this is really going to unlock paid
acquisition and some other things such
as the marginal cost of AI features for
us, then why not do it? It gives our
marketing team so much more room to
operate. Since you did these experiments
way back in 2024 and you didn't fully
adopt that new price until 2026, I
imagine you have a lot of data to be
able to look at retention. One of the
things about increasing price is that in
RevenueCat's data that we share in the
report, we do see higher retention at
lower prices. Now, that's not always
going to be the case, you know,
sometimes higher price products do
retain better, but just in general, we
do see that in the data. And so, I do
think that's something a lot of apps do
face. And so, have you found retention
to
at least break even as well? Yeah, I'd
say our our retention is very stable.
And I think that's because
even though we
are getting less new premium users
because of the higher price, our free
product is amazing. Since the beginning,
we actually operated from 2008 to 2012
without a paid product. So, our product
has always been a freemium model and our
free product has always been
very useful to people. We invest a lot
in it.
We make sure that the free product is a
great experience. The premium product is
just that much better.
I I
you know, if people are more more
motivated,
they can get the premium features and
that helps them out a lot, but you can
do everything you need to do to lose
weight in the free product and we're
very proud of that. You've talked about
a couple things being huge unlocks for
raising the price, you know, being able
to tolerate higher CAC. You've talked
about the AI features where, you know,
the incremental cost of serving these
users is getting higher as you increase
the cost of servicing some of these
features. What other unlocks have you
seen from being able to raise the price?
Yeah, over the years we built quite a
lifecycle sale mechanism and it's a
homegrown system that we built into the
app and refined over years and years.
So, how much of a discount a user gets
at a certain point in their journey is
completely built into the experience.
And the higher price point allows us to
offer more discounts to more users and
try to get more area under the curve
there because from zero to 40, there's
not as much room to do, you know, 50,
25%, 75% discounts, but at $80, we can
do more steep discounting and everyone
knows about the sale psychology,
you know, the bigger the percent,
usually the higher the conversion even
in absolute dollars,
you know, the price is higher. How did
the product team react to the increase
in price? Cuz I know there can sometimes
be a tension between kind of the the
revenue and monetization optimization
from like the the product people maybe
have a more kind of purity mindset of
like, oh, you know, like we want to make
it a good deal for the users and stuff.
>> Yeah, the product team was fully on
board and they were actually pushing for
it. They did everything they could to
enable this because I think the way they
look at it is that all of our main
competitors are around the $80 price
point. And not to disparage any of our
competitors, but we believe our product
is just as good as theirs.
However, our price didn't really reflect
that. They felt like they were doing
work that was just as valuable to users
as our other competitors work, but it
but it wasn't being reflected in the
price. And what what are prices if not
information about how something valuable
is.
>> Yeah. I was just talking to somebody
about about pricing and how in the app
space, it's not like a shelf at a
grocery store where people are looking
at the like Campbell's soup and then the
store brand soup and doing the math and
like picking based on price. You know,
people are coming in from ads and so
they don't necessarily have that like
frame of reference anyway. And so even
when you think about a lower price being
a differentiator,
it's not necessarily because people
aren't necessarily price shopping in
that same way, especially once you're
pushing deeper into uh paid user
acquisition, you're probably getting
less of that price comparison anyway.
That's true. Uh I will say that that
with the caveat of that, our lower price
point did help us, I think, during the
early stages of the pandemic. Right.
>> When people were
trapped in their houses, unsure how they
were going to meet their health and
fitness goals, but also unsure of their
financial situation cuz
I I know we don't like to go back and
remember what it was like in March and
April of 2020, but we had no idea what
was going to happen. And so I think
being a low-cost option really benefited
us then.
But since I I I think you're absolutely
right. Like we we haven't seen any I
don't think there's too much comparison
shopping going on either, which is what
another reason why this is working. I'm
wondering if if you did consider a
higher tier of price versus raising the
price for everybody and and why you
decided against doing that. Uh we're
considering all options.
Uh higher higher tier is not off the
table. Uh we've since implemented, you
know, ad-based
monetization in the free product. Uh
we're looking to monetize in all sorts
of ways. We've added in-app purchases,
one-off in-app purchases in the app.
We've added partnerships in the app, you
know, affiliate revenue. So, nothing's
off the table. I would say we have not
decided against that.
We're we're always open to new ideas to
monetize. But the decision was to raise
the the floor, raise the the main
primary subscription price. And that
still leaves the opportunity to to add
tiers on top and and explore other
monetization.
Exactly, yeah. We have such a lo- a
loyal
user base. Uh we love our users and they
love us and um there's a subset of
users who want the very best Loseit has
to offer. If we work really hard and
create a product that generates a lot of
value, we have a lot of great users who
are totally on board with that. That's
awesome. And you one thing you didn't do
was raise prices on existing users,
which is always such a tough decision.
I've heard it go both ways. I've heard
some people say they doubled prices and
it was just and they didn't grandfather
users and because their customer base
was so loyal, they just made way more
money and you know, they saw some churn,
but but it was, you know, significantly
offset by the increase of the price. Why
did you choose not to? Yeah, there were
a few reasons why. So,
the way that you have to increase the
price on existing subscriptions in the
App Store, I feel like the UX is
confusing and cumbersome. I think you
get like a notification that says, "When
you renew, you know, the price is going
to go up." And then they have to go to
the App Store and either opt in or not
opt in. I didn't feel like that was a
good experience for our users. To us, it
was impossible to AB test. Yeah. It was
a huge risk for us that we felt like we
couldn't take on. Like, what is the
attrition rate when you raise the price
of an existing subscription? I don't
know.
That might be in the State of the
Subscription Apps Report. I don't know,
but to us, it's like we couldn't risk
it. Like, is it 75%? Is it 25%? It was
just too too big of an unknown for us.
And also, we've always had a history of
whenever we've made policy or product
changes over the years to grandfather in
our loyal users. When we were at the App
Growth Annual in October, our growth
person and one of our product managers,
Danielle and Burton, presented on how we
moved the barcode scanner from behind
the paywall. When we actually made that
change, we grandfathered in free users
to that change. And that change was only
for new users as well.
We've always had just a tradition of
doing that just because, again, we we
love our users and we feel like whatever
bargain they entered into, whatever they
came to us, we try to keep as much as
possible. Yeah, and then I mean, there
is that incentive. I've talked about
this on the podcast before. I got in
some special deal with Headspace where
it was I think I was paying like $3 a
month or something. And then at that
time, the price had gone up to $12 a
month or $60 a year. And I knew if I
canceled, when I resubscribed, I'd have
to pay a lot more. And so, I stuck with
that subscription even though I wasn't
even using the app much at the time
because there was that incentive to
stick around. So, I think there is a
little bit of that, too, with your
grandfathered users. And then I would
assume that if they do churn and come
back to the app, then they're going to
see that new price and have to pay that
higher price, right? Right. So, I think
that's an interesting experiment we can
run right off the bat, right? Like if
someone has marked a cheaper
subscription to not renew, you know, we
can have an intervention there that is
like, "Are you sure?" Because
>> Yes.
it's going to be different. You've had
about a month of rolling out this new
price to everyone, and it was like kind
of the most important month for a health
and fitness app. So, Yes.
>> what are the early signs of having
rolled this out across the the entire
user base?
I would say so far the results have been
exactly our experiment results, which
hardly ever happens, right? Like usually
Usually when you release something out
in the wild, it's like a little bit
different, but so far it it has held up
to our experiment results, and that that
is a credit to our growth marketing team
and our product team. They really tested
this rigorously, really analyzed the
data. And so, so far it's been holding
up very, very well. Uh we're very
excited about it.
>> Awesome. Well, I think it's a great
place to wrap up. Uh anything you wanted
to share as we wrap up? Uh I'll put a a
link to uh Lose It and your LinkedIn in
the show notes, but anything else you
want to shout out as we wrap up? Yeah.
Uh we need iOS developers. So,
>> [laughter]
>> if you are an iOS developer, please
please seek me out on LinkedIn. We're
trying to grow. We're trying to do a lot
of things. Uh we need people. Uh it's a
really cool team. I've met a lot of
folks behind Lose It, and uh really like
everyone I've talked to. So, yeah, it's
been been great. You know, the the App
Growth Annual has been a really fun
place to to meet folks from the
industry. And so, over I think I've met
six or eight people now from the Lose It
team between App Growth Annual and other
events and stuff. So, great team. If you
are an iOS developer and know a good
one, uh I can I can say it's good
people. Good people and a cool product.
So, Well, thank you very much.
>> [music]
>> Thanks so much for listening.
If you have a minute, please leave a
review in your favorite podcast player.
You can also stop by chat.subclub.com
to join our private community.
>> [music]